Oh, okay.
Where are we now?
Got the VRI for our
deaf patient in Central 12.
Still waiting on Pedes
for Baby Jane Doe.
Central six is sitting pretty
with his insulin drip.
And the Westbridge
diversions are
kindly waiting
their turn to sit
for hours in our lovely halls.
You are some kind of savant.
Worthy of a raise?
Just more of my love.
I got enough of that.
I have a sexual
assault victim in triage.
I called PAAR,
so an advocate is on the way.
Okay. We'll take care of it.
Uh, Dr. McKay, what's going on
with your patient in Central nine?
Isn't she good to go?
Oh, she was, but she decided
she wanted to stay
in the hospital now
because she's in too much pain.
In our loud
and overcrowded ED
with more Westbridge cases
arriving every moment?
She would be
more comfortable at home.
The debrief was lovely.
Thank you.
Would you mind helping Dana
with a sexual assault victim
who just came in?
- Of course. Sure.
Why don't you and I go
see if we can't convince
your patient to leave?
- All right.
I need to take care of a sexual
assault victim in triage.
One of you needs
to hold down the fort.
- We can call for a SANE.
- On a holiday? Could be hours.
We're not gonna make
this patient wait.
And since I'm the only
SANE on staff--
Princess will cover.
[Speaking Tagalog]
Hey! Hey!
You two better not be
teaching her any bad habits.
Come on. You ready, Doc?
- Sure.
A SANE is a Sexual Assault
Nurse Examiner.
We do forensic exams,
collect evidence,
and hand it over to the police
if a report is made.
We also provide
resources, support,
sometimes even testimony.
- You go to court?
SANEs are very valuable in
a hospital, especially an ED.
More nurses should
train for it.
That's a not so subtle hint.
[Phone ringing]
[indistinct conversations]
Looks like this is
the new hot spot, huh?
And only getting hotter.
Any word on what's
going on with Westbridge?
I got 20 on lantern flies.
Nope, nothing.
These patient passports have
an interesting alternative use.
Where's the sexual
assault victim?
She's in Triage, Chair two.
Thanks, Lupe.
Here's her intake.
Got it.
[Sighs]
Hi, Ms. Miller.
I'm Dana.
How are you doing?
- I've been better.
- Yeah.
You're in a safe place now.
I'm the charge nurse in the ED
and a sexual assault
nurse examiner.
This is Emma,
who will be assisting.
And I'm Dr. Al-Hashimi.
I'll be checking you
for any injuries
that need immediate attention.
You can just call me Ilana.
I don't have any injuries.
Okay, that's good.
We're gonna get
a room ready for you.
Meanwhile, Dr. Al-Hashimi is
gonna ask you a few questions.
How long is this gonna take?
I can't promise
an exact time,
but we'll try to be
as fast as you need.
- Thank you.
- Yeah.
Okay, Ilana, do you take any
prescription medications?
Just Synthroid,
one tab a day.
Okay, and any allergies
to medications?
- No. No.
- Okay.
Dana will come get you
when the room is ready,
and I'll be back
to finish your exam.
Come find me
when she's in a gown.
Will do.
We're gonna use Triage Exam
Rooms one and two for this.
It's the most private space
we have away from the ED.
All right, this can be a lot.
You up for it?
Yeah.
Yes. I'm good.
Let me know if
you need to step out.
[Sighs] Yes.
Dr. Ellis.
- Oh, no.
- Oh, yes.
Need the room.
Find another place
to lay your head.
Not even
a 20-minute power nap?
You know, my double is at 1:30.
I'm--
Nope, we're getting
Westbridge diversions.
And chairs is insane.
Did you see out there?
- No.
I do not come in
through that mess.
Okay.
Yeah.
People sleep in here?
Yeah, the night shift docs
just need rest,
especially if they have to
come in during the day.
But today, we can't
waste the space.
I need you to get me a stool on
wheels and Esme for a turnover.
So you're having a headache
and abdominal pain?
Yeah, that's right.
Okay, and which would
you say is worse?
My headache was terrible
last week...
[Voice distorting]
But now--[static crackles]
- Hey, you're--
You're breaking up.
Can you run that back again?
Sure.
[Clears throat]
My headache was terrible
last week...
[Voice distorting]
But now my abdominal pain--
Oh, my God.
Come on, you piece of--
Fuck.
Um--
I'll--
- I'll be right back.
Sorry.
Um, Dr. Al-Hashimi?
Jackson's parents are here.
Okay. I'll take that.
Um, Mr. and Mrs. Davis,
this is one of my attendings,
Dr. Al-Hashimi.
- Hi. Nice to meet you.
- Demi.
- Charles.
What the hell's going on?
He's barely conscious.
Jackson's just a little tired
due to the sedative
he was given.
- You sedated him?
Oh, your son was brought in
extremely agitated.
You'd be, too,
if you were tased.
And why the fuck
did they do that?
This is bullshit.
We're taking him home.
Why don't we step out
for a second?
Right now, Jackson is on
an involuntary psych hold.
- What?
That's not necessary.
He just needs some rest.
He's been studying
for the bar exam.
We can watch him at home.
So far, all of his tests
look good,
but Jackson has
reported hearing voices.
This could be serious.
Dr. Jefferson will come back
and speak with you.
He can explain more of what
may be going on with Jackson.
And who is Dr. Jefferson?
He's from Psychiatry,
and he's excellent.
He can explain next steps and
answer all of your questions.
Javadi, why don't you take
the Davises to the family room?
- Sure.
- Excuse me.
It's just this way.
[Soft tense music]
[Sighs shakily]
[line trills]
You have reached the
Pittsburgh Neuroscience Group.
If this is
a medical emergency,
please hang up and dial 911.
For our address and
office hours, press one.
To refill a prescription,
press two.
To leave a message for
the doctor on call--
Hi, this is
Dr. Baran al-Hashimi.
I'm a patient
of Dr. Fairgraves.
I need to speak to him
if he's on call.
If he's not, I'll take his
next available appointment.
And please call me
if he has a cancellation.
Thank you.
Like I said, you're more than
welcome to stay down here
until an inpatient bed
opens up upstairs.
But that can take a while,
sometimes days,
even longer.
It's gonna be
really noisy here,
and you won't get any rest.
At home, you'll be
surrounded by your family
and be more comfortable.
It's your choice, Roxie.
It's not that
I don't wanna go home, but--
- Hi, Mom.
- Mom.
- Lena texted me to come back.
I figured I'd bring the boys.
What's going on?
Is everything okay?
Robby, police officer,
incoming trauma.
Coming.
I'll be right back.
We'll give you
a chance to talk.
Okay, why don't you
have a seat?
Do you need anything
before we begin?
You're in control now, Ilana.
We're here to help
and support you.
Once I open this kit,
I cannot leave the room.
But if you need a break
or some air, just let us know.
Okay? Emma can go
with you if you like.
An advocate from
Pittsburgh Action Against Rape
has been called,
and they should arrive soon.
- Can we start?
- Sure.
I'm gonna put my face shield on
so I don't
contaminate anything.
Emma has already done the same.
Now, in order for the doctor
to do her exam,
I need you in a gown,
but I need to collect
your clothing first.
Is that okay?
I'm gonna need you to undress
on top of these pads.
Put each item of clothing
on the pads, okay?
Then we'll package each piece
in a separate bag.
We'll get you new clothes.
Don't worry.
- All right.
Emma's gonna be
behind this curtain,
and I'll be in here with you.
And take off your shoes first.
When you're done,
I want you to put on your gown
open in the back.
[Breathing in]
What if the mom
doesn't wanna leave?
Well, then she's gonna
have to put up with us.
[Sighs]
I can't imagine--her boys.
Oh, don't go there.
I'm gonna see if
I can grease the wheels,
get her a room upstairs soon.
- Good luck.
What was that?
Battle plan
for our hall space.
It's filling up fast.
Police officer should
be here any minute.
Yeah, well, as soon
as you can, please,
I need you to fix the VRI.
All right. Thanks.
Santos, I need you
to pick up some more
of these Westbridge diversions.
- Sure.
You want my firstborn too?
- Maybe.
Will they know how to suture?
Intubated neck wound,
sats not great.
We were diverted here.
Is there a trauma room open?
- Trauma one!
- What's the story?
My buddy, Officer Hiro,
high-velocity GSW.
He's getting harder to bag.
Warehouse robbery
gone sideways.
One, two, three.
You guys wait here.
We'll take care of him,
I promise.
I thought you left us
already for the open road?
And miss seeing you
in uniform?
You should see me
as a flight attendant.
- Did you do this intubation?
- Under active fire, yeah.
Are you serious?
I go in with the team
in case there's an injury.
That's badass.
Dr. Santos, let's make sure
these lungs are up.
Could you see the cords?
- Yeah, there was a great view,
but it was hard to pass
after I cleared them.
Yeah, sats down to 85.
Dr. Santos, what could
cause respiratory failure
in an intubated patient?
There are a lot
of possibilities.
Think DOPE.
Displacement, Obstruction,
Pneumothorax,
Equipment failure.
Good lung sliding, no pneumo.
It is displacement.
Okay, that is
a transected trachea.
[Grunting]
Pulling out.
Bag.
But if you intubate again,
won't it just come straight
out the wound?
- Yep, exactly.
So we're gonna
need another plan.
Okay. Sats down to 83.
Yeah, he's not
moving any air.
Okay, I need a neonatal mask.
- Neonatal?
- Yep.
I'm just going to finish
my initial exam.
Let me know if you
feel any pain, okay?
My legs are fine.
All looks good.
No need for X-rays
or advanced imaging.
Got it.
- Two areas of ecchymosis...
- That means bruising.
Over the shoulders
bilaterally.
- I'll document with photos.
- Okay.
Dana will finish up her work,
and I will be in the ER
if you have any questions.
You're in great hands.
Thank you.
All right, Ilana.
I read your intake.
Why don't you give me
your description
of exactly what happened?
I was at
a 4th of July barbecue
with a bunch of friends.
I helped set up.
[Sniffles]
Where does it hurt?
Like here,
under my belly button.
Okay, do you have any fever,
vomiting, diarrhea?
- Oh, no.
It's--it's just a stomachache.
Okay, well, still, go see
the nurse and have her call me.
Okay.
But I'm still having
ice cream tonight.
Why don't you see
how you feel later?
- It--it's not bad.
You don't have to get so sad.
- I'm not sad.
I'm--
- I'm good.
Your face doesn't look good.
Oh.
Well, you still wanna watch
the fireworks tonight?
[Siren whoops]
I have our headphones--
[Speaking Tamil]
- I'm not being rude.
- Sorry, Becca. I gotta go.
Elliot Green, 17, syncopal
episode at football practice.
Look, I just got dizzy, okay?
It's hell week.
I need to get back.
Yeah, okay, tough guy.
A and O, systolic of 95, tachy
at 122, no meds, no allergies.
How long were you
at practice?
I started at 9:00,
so, like, four hours.
Four hours in this heat
with all that gear?
No pain, no game.
God, I'm hungry.
Hey. When's our break?
- There's no breaks down here.
Always make sure you pack
a protein bar, something quick.
Ogilvie, Joy,
jump in on this.
Syncope at football practice.
- No, I just--
I just needed to hydrate.
Possible heatstroke?
Well, with heatstroke,
you would have
an altered mental status.
And they're usually dry,
not sweaty.
Mortality is 50%,
especially in the elderly.
In extreme heat like this...
Langdon, can you cover this?
- No problem.
- Mr. Diaz. Orlando.
Orlando, where are you going?
- Home. Can you take these out?
- Uh, no.
It takes 48 hours for you
to get out of DKA.
Your blood is still
full of acid.
Look, I can't add
thousands of dollars
to the 100 grand I already owe.
- I'm--
- I'm sorry.
100 grand?
- In medical debt.
My wife doesn't even know.
I'll never be able
to pay it off as it is.
Where are your wife
and daughter?
Maybe we can all talk.
I told them to go back
to work a couple hours ago.
But the hospital is
giving you a big discount.
And, Mr. Diaz,
I know it's not ideal,
but can you stay
for at least 12 hours?
It would get you out
of the danger zone.
No. I really can't.
Every minute I stay is a meal,
shoes, school supplies.
Plus, I have a second job
I have to get to by 4:00.
- You need fluids!
- I drink plenty of water.
- And potassium and insulin.
Okay, how about this?
You stay and I'll get together
everything you'll need at home.
Also, a referral to Northside
Christian Health Center.
Come on.
You don't work until 4:00.
It'll keep you from passing out
on the job again--
Or worse.
Okay, I guess.
Great.
Thank you. Please.
[Sighs]
Sats up to 98.
- Neonatal mask is working.
- Santos, finish the FAST.
What--what are
you injecting?
Lido with epi.
It'll clamp off
any little bleeders.
- We need some skin hooks.
Four Shiley?
Mm, I don't like
the curve of a Shiley.
I didn't know
you were so picky.
Santos, take a break.
Help me cut down a 6-0 ET tube.
What is going on here?
You have a field medic
assisting you?
Dr. Abbot is an attending,
and he's also a SWAT physician.
My buddy Hiro here
is in bad need of an airway.
Cut it right here.
- We can do this.
No, no, I got it.
You must be Gloria's new hire.
Yes. Dr. Al-Hashimi.
Well, I'd shake your hand,
but my tube is ready.
And if I could find
and secure the distal trachea,
we have a shot at this.
Okay, keeping
an eye on the sats.
- Slow is smooth.
Smooth is fast.
You know, you can call me
just to say hi sometimes.
What's up now?
GSW with tracheal
transection.
Very retracted,
but I think I can get it.
- Both lungs are up?
[Monitor beeping]
- Sats down to 91.
- Scanning the belly now.
Okay.
I got it. I got it.
Gently, gently,
or we're gonna lose it.
Down to 89.
Oh, no.
I'm in. Balloon up.
End tidal,
excellent wave form.
Good breath sounds.
I'll sew the tracheal
to the skin, 2-0 silk.
- Sats are coming up.
- Whoo.
Not bad, Abbot.
- [Exhales]
Mm, while you were playing
with that airway,
you missed a big bruise
in the left upper quadrant.
He was wearing body armor.
High-velocity projectile
doesn't have
to penetrate to damage.
There's no fluid
in the suprasplenic space.
Let me look.
Okay, right there.
Looks like a subcapsular
hematoma of his spleen.
Must have been a big impact.
AR-15 muzzle velocity
is 3,000 feet per second.
CT angio of the neck ASAP,
along with CT chest,
abdomen, pelvis.
Yep, just as soon
as we secure this tube.
- First liter's in.
- Mucous membranes dry.
Pupils four millimeters
reactive.
Did you get tackled today?
No, just running drills.
- Any chest pain?
Palpitations?
No.
Hands off, please,
running the 12 lead.
How are we looking?
Good. Healthy kid.
No history, no trauma.
Differential for syncope
in an adolescent?
Cardiac arrhythmia
from drugs...
- Hypovolemia, seizure...
- Long QT, WPW...
- Sepsis.
- Or Brugada.
Uh, Brugada is more
common in Asian males.
But still
should be considered.
Long odds, though.
Brugada prevalence is
one in 20,000 in North America,
as high as one in 300 in Asia
and the Middle East.
And?
First described in 1992,
has a high incidence
of sudden death among
young patients with otherwise
structurally normal hearts--
- Oof, oof, wait.
Did you just say
"sudden death"?
Temp is 102.5.
Sorry, our student doctors
are discussing
a rare condition
you don't have.
- I--
- I just didn't
drink enough water.
I overheated.
Not my type, bud.
Other than standard labs,
what else to order?
CK to rule out rhabdo.
To make sure you don't have
any muscle breakdown
from the heat.
Let's set up a cooling room
for Elliot here
and the other heat exhaustions
we'll inevitably get today.
Last photo.
[Camera shutter clicks]
Okay.
We'll take the SD card
and seal it
in an evidence envelope
with everything else.
Okay.
Next, Emma's gonna
turn off the light,
and I'll run a blue light
over your skin.
Anything glows, I'll swab it
with a wet, then dry Q-tip.
Is that okay?
Yeah, sure.
All right.
Take off your gown
on the left side
and turn a little bit
towards me, just to the left.
There.
Something on the left wrist.
Swab.
[Sighs deeply]
Sorry.
Don't be.
- It's just cold.
- Yeah.
Almost done.
[Beeping]
- Thanks, Antoine.
- No problem.
Keep your head down out there.
What's the story?
Neck angio is negative,
missed the carotids.
- He's lucky.
- What about the belly?
Small splenic injury,
no free fluid in the abdomen.
- That should heal on its own.
- What's the plan?
Head and Neck will have
an OR ready
with thoracic standing by.
How soon can they take him?
We're a little backed up
with Westbridge patients,
but let's bring him up.
I'll get him
taken care of for you.
Hey.
You're gonna be okay, Hiro.
We're getting you to surgery.
I'll write
the procedure note.
Thank you.
SWAT? Really?
I suck at golf.
You spend time
in the Middle East?
More than I would have liked.
I worked in Kabul
with Médecins Sans Frontières
and in 2020,
at the maternity hospital.
I met the most incredible,
bravest doctors there.
Dasht-e-Barchi.
Tragedy.
We should grab a beer sometime,
share war stories.
I'd like that.
She seems cool.
Yep, maybe.
I'm not gonna be around
long enough to find out.
Oh, there she is! Vic!
Dad!
Victoria,
this is Dr. Amy Joon.
Dr. Joon is the smartest
person I know.
Don't tell your mother.
Just kidding.
[Laughs]
But seriously, don't.
- [Laughs] Hi.
- Hello.
Are--are you here
to see a patient?
- No.
We're here to see you.
Dr. Joon is Chief
of Dermatology.
And Victoria's first
shift in the ER
was on the day
of the PittFest shooting.
I heard all
the incredible stories,
including your own acts
of med student prowess.
Wow, med student prowess.
That's--[laughs]
I'm--
- I'm pretty sure
I was just trying
to stay out of the way.
Ah, she's modest,
like her dad.
- And her mother?
[Phone rings]
Oh. Sorry.
Dr. Joon.
Yep, coming.
I'm doing a favor for someone
at the mayor's office
who needs Mohs surgery
on a basal cell carcinoma.
And then I am grilling for 30.
- Oh, wow.
- Happy 4th, all.
- Happy 4th.
- Yeah. [laughs]
- Thanks for coming down.
- My pleasure.
Let's grab a coffee sometime.
- Absolutely. Yes.
Thank you.
You know Mom really wants me
to go into surgery.
Ah, your mom wants me
to stop drinking
and join a pickleball league.
- Oh, that's the same.
- Yeah, well--
- Exact same.
I will risk an Achilles tear
before I give up scotch.
[Chuckles] Hey, I hope I didn't
embarrass you coming down here.
No.
I'm just trying to present
you with some options
for your residency.
- I--
- I really
appreciate it, Dad.
I do.
I just--
I'm still not sure.
Well, either way,
you'll do what's right.
You always do.
Proud of ya.
- Okay.
Dr. Javadi, you are
a man of many talents.
- [Laughs]
You don't know the half of it.
- [Chuckles]
Your daughter has some
high standards to live up to.
Oh, you don't know
the half of it.
Mr. and Mrs. Davis, this is
Dr. Jefferson from Psychiatry.
Please call me Caleb.
Can you tell us what's
going on with our son?
All of his labs
and X-rays came back normal.
Given his age
and his hearing voices,
do either of you have a family
history of mental illness?
Not mine.
[Clears throat]
My brother took his own life.
Wait, what?
Uncle Ken?
You said he drank
himself to death.
Ma.
- He did that too.
Was he ever
formally diagnosed
with a mental health issue?
No.
He was depressed,
had mood swings.
But he didn't wanna see anyone.
- Oh, my God.
Okay, why am I just now
hearing about this?
- Jada, please.
- Please what, Mom?
Why would you not
tell Jackson or me?
[Scoffs]
I can't believe this.
- Jada.
- Excuse me.
Jada.
What happens next?
We keep your son here
for the next three days
for observation and therapy.
And that will help us
to understand what is going on.
Jada should really hear this.
Let me see if I can find her,
bring her back.
- Okay.
I'm gonna swab your mouth now.
My mouth?
Two dry swabs along
the inside of your cheek
and then along the gum line.
How you feeling?
I wish this day
never happened.
Would you like some medicine
to help you relax?
You've experienced
a horrific trauma.
You've been
doing this a while?
Let's just say
Florence Nightingale
and I were roommates.
- Who?
- [Chuckles]
I rest my case.
She was the founder
of modern nursing.
Okay, you can have something
to eat or drink now.
- I'm fine.
- Are you sure?
I'll just keep going.
Okay.
We now have a heat exhaustion
treatment area in North five.
- Evaporated cooling.
Great plan.
Yeah, it was
Dr. Langdon's idea.
He figured we'd be seeing a lot
more patients in this heat.
He's right.
How are you feeling?
- [Sighs]
That's a loaded question.
It wasn't meant to be.
You have a deposition
in a couple of hours?
- Yes.
- How are you feeling about it?
Um, trying
to think positively
but feeling, um, less so.
This job's really important
to me and my sister.
You know, I support both of us.
It's gonna go great.
Just tell them what happened.
You're not at fault.
Your job's not in jeopardy.
I mean, the lawyers
said that I could--
The lawyers' job is to try
and shake your confidence.
So don't let them.
You're a very good doctor.
I have been training
residents for years.
You are one of the very best.
I am?
No, we need
to stick to the plan.
- I promise.
- Look.
Thanks.
She's not thinking
clearly, okay?
It's gonna be great.
This is not what she wants.
Then I'm taking her home.
That's it.
We have to honor
your wife's wishes.
Even if she's
loaded up on morphine
and can't think straight?
- Especially then.
Hello.
Paul Hamler, this is
my attending, Dr. Robinavitch.
- Hi.
Uh, my wife is not
thinking clearly.
What is it that
she's asking for?
Said she wants to stay here.
Why don't we all
go in and talk?
Brian Jenkins is
allowed to hunt with a .22
on his grandpa's farm.
Sounds like an accident
just waiting to happen.
- Mm-hmm.
And you're not Brian Jenkins.
How are we doing
in here, Roxie?
Been better.
Rumor has it
you're still interested
in booking a room with us?
I don't wanna
go back home yet.
It's all set up, Rox.
You're gonna be
more comfortable at home.
Paul, I changed my mind.
It is our home.
I don't--
I don't want you
living with my ghost.
I will happily
live with your ghost.
Can we just all stop
talking about ghosts, please?
Yes. I'm sorry.
I'm sorry, sweetie.
You're right.
- Got trauma flying in.
ETA, five minutes.
- Okay.
Um, I'm very sorry.
I will be right back.
Excuse me.
It's a boating accident,
swimmer versus propeller.
Ouch.
What body parts involved?
- They didn't say.
- How old?
- Nope.
Anything?
All I got was
boating accident,
swimmer versus propeller.
- Propeller. Got it.
[Elevator dings]
[helicopter whirring]
Picked a hell of a day
to come back, huh?
How's Jake?
He's good.
He's better. He's coping.
He's gonna be
a senior this fall.
That's great.
That was a lot
for him to go through.
A lot for all of us
to go through.
Yeah.
Okay, I'm just gonna say it!
I'm sorry.
I betrayed your trust.
I betrayed our patients' trust.
And I'm really fucking sorry.
It'll never happen again,
I swear.
I'm really glad that you
got the help that you need.
But I don't know if
I want you working in my ER.
[Elevator dings]
Why'd you intubate him?
He was splinting
from the pain,
barely moving air
with sats in the 80s.
How'd he get sliced up
in the propeller?
He was in the Allegheny
trying to untangle
a water ski tow line
when his buddy
started the engine.
Drunk buddy, I assume?
- Well, it's 4th of July.
You tell me.
Focus on the patient, please.
Sofie, take over bagging.
Okay. One, two, three.
Watch that buckle.
- Do you need me in here?
- Nope.
We have a senior resident
and an attending.
Mel, can we start with a--
- An EFAST? Sure.
- Yes, please.
Why?
To check and make sure
there's no pneumothorax.
Otherwise, it could
become a tension.
Exactly. Oh, wow.
You want O-neg?
- Not without a BP first.
108/64, pulse is 102.
Sats are good.
- Okay, let's have O-neg ready,
but don't give it just yet.
- Anything else?
[Alarm blaring]
How about a hemocue?
- Uh, yeah.
Yeah, yeah, of course.
Next step is fingernails.
We'll go under each nail,
first with the wet swab
and then with the dry one.
Do you wanna take a break, hon?
No.
[Breathing shakily]
How much longer?
After these,
we'll get to external...
[Knock at door]
And internal
vaginal collection.
It's the advocate from PAAR.
They've been doing this
longer than I have.
They provide resources,
assistance, and support
for sexual assault survivors.
Hey.
This will not define you, okay?
You don't have to talk to them,
but I recommend you do.
They're available 24/7.
- Okay.
Hi.
I'm Paulette Sanderson from
Pittsburgh Action Against Rape.
- Hi, Paulette.
I'm the SANE, Dana.
And this is Ilana.
- Hello.
I'm sorry to meet you
under these circumstances,
but I and my organization
are here to help you navigate
everything that comes next.
I brought you some clothes
and basic necessities.
I can even stay with you
through the rest
of your examination
if you'd like.
I don't think
that's necessary.
- Okay.
- That's fine.
Would it be okay if
I asked you a few questions?
Sure.
[Phone rings]
Mm, our VRI isn't working.
Video Relay Interpreter?
Yeah, of course I rebooted it.
Wait, how are you gonna
fix it if you don't know
what the hell it is?
Yeah, okay.
Whatever.
I wanna do a head
and belly scan on Harlow.
Can you try telling her why?
What about the VRI?
It's DOA.
I'm charting every
free minute I get.
I wasn't coming over
for that.
Good job in the Trauma earlier.
What's this?
Daniel Scott, 32,
weak and dizzy
while washing his car.
Tachy at 106, BP 90/60.
Temp's too high to register.
We have a cooling room
set up in North five.
Okay, how are you
feeling, Mr. Scott?
Thirsty.
Let's see if
we can't fix that.
He's gonna need a core temp,
a CMP--whoa.
Oh, hey, we need
a trauma room.
What's open?
- Two.
I'll grab the Ativan.
- Any past medical history?
- No.
Wife says he's healthy.
No meds, no allergies.
He needs a core temp.
Ready to transfer.
Let's give two of Ativan.
Don't want him seizing again.
I gotta get back
to my patients.
Okay.
One, two, three.
Orders?
Second IV with saline open.
Sepsis panel, UA,
urine drug screen, EKG, and CK.
I don't see any
apparent trauma.
[Alarms ringing]
Pupils reactive.
- Mr. Scott? Daniel?
Can you talk to me?
Post-ictal,
but moving all extremities.
Pulse 137, BP 88/60.
What are you thinking,
Dr. Santos?
Uh, heat stroke,
but consider sepsis or drugs.
Rectal temp is 104.6.
All right, let's start
with four ice packs
on the groin and axilla.
Should we do
a full body ice bath?
- That'll take too long.
Do you have an Arctic Sun?
Yeah, we do.
Get pads on the chest,
abdomen, and both legs.
I'll check back in.
Ceftazidime is up,
and first hemoglobin, 8.2.
- Eight is pretty low.
He must have bled down from 14.
Anything you
wanna do about that?
- Um, young, healthy guy.
We transfuse at seven.
Do we?
We'd be in real trouble
if he equilibrates
from acute blood loss.
- Am I interrupting something?
- Multiple deep lacerations--
- Motorboat versus--
Jesus.
This looks like some
"Jurassic Park" shit.
Is that your official
surgical diagnosis?
He is hemodynamically stable.
What else do we know?
Uh, intubated in the field
due to poor tidal volume.
EFAST was negative
for pneumothorax,
so no need to do a chest tube.
And no free fluid
in the abdomen,
good hemostasis
inside the wounds.
Nothing arterial.
At first, he had
a hemoglobin of 8.2.
We'll follow that closely.
With no active bleeding,
I wouldn't transfuse just yet.
Dr. Langdon agrees with you.
Let's get him to CT.
Jason Stills, 62,
was gathering the makings
of a salad when he started
feeling dizzy and nauseated.
Vomited once.
How are you feeling,
Mr. Stills?
Like I'm gonna die.
Well, you came to the right
place to prevent that.
Do you mind
if I touch your abdomen?
- Yeah, sure.
- Okay.
Does this hurt at all?
- No.
He's tachycardic at 124
with a temp of 102.4.
Hey, Joy,
what's your suggestion?
Keep hydrating,
check electrolytes,
and move him
to the cooling room.
Precisely.
Good luck finding
a parking spot.
- North five.
- What? No valet?
[Elevator dings]
Jada. Hey.
I--I've been looking
all over for you.
I just went for a walk.
I wanted to talk to you,
if that's okay.
So does Dr. Jefferson.
It's important that you get
to hear what he has to say.
Why?
He doesn't want me to go crazy
like my brother?
Or kill myself like my uncle?
Of course not.
We--we still have no idea
what caused Jackson's episode.
- [Sighs]
Episode.
Right.
- Look, I--
- I know this
must be so scary for you.
And you probably feel
betrayed by your parents.
But they had no way
of knowing about Jackson.
You know, and some families
just have a difficult time
talking about mental health.
Now you can help us
take the first steps
to finding out what we can
do to help your brother.
Mr. Diaz,
I have a surprise for you.
Oh.
Sorry.
It's okay.
Have you--have you
seen my patient?
Orlando? Mr. Diaz?
Room was empty.
- Seriously?
- Yeah.
[Sighs]
What happened to you?
Oh.
Bullet grazed my vest.
You were shot?
Shot at.
Geniuses thought today was the
day to rob a goods warehouse.
Didn't think about
how long it would take
to load the appliances.
They panicked.
All hell broke loose.
Jesus.
Why do you do this?
My therapist said
I needed a hobby.
Funny.
[Sighs deeply]
Shit.
This--this sucks.
- Oh, it's nothing.
- No.
- No, don't worry about me.
I'm fine. Seriously.
No, my patient.
He didn't have any insurance,
and he was already
in a mountain of medical debt.
He couldn't afford
any of his meds.
Hmm.
What's in the bag?
Insulin, test strips,
electrolyte powder.
I--I got him everything
he needed for home care.
So Uber it to his house.
Is the hospital
gonna pay for that?
I'll pay for it.
What are you doing?
What you clearly can't.
Did you make a chart?
No.
This can stay off the books.
Don't need the paperwork
from the hospital
or the police department.
Okay.
Our little secret.
- How's he doing?
Any more seizures?
Nope.
Temp 102.9.
Labs back?
Mostly signs of dehydration.
A tad hypernatremic,
mild BUN and creatinine bump.
- CK 400 something--
Nothing worrisome yet.
Okay, good. Keep cooling.
- I'll monitor him.
- Great.
That'll give Dr. Santos
a chance to get caught up.
Your R2 year
can be challenging.
You just have to keep grinding.
What's your dispo plan
for Mr. Scott?
Uh, ICU admission.
You should call Neurology
to consult.
Yeah, done.
Since it was exertional heat
illness in a young person,
the mortality is low.
But non-exertional heatstroke
in an elderly person,
you need to worry.
- Okay.
I'll put in orders
for repeat labs.
Good work in there.
[Sighs]
This 49-year-old woman presents
to the emergency department--
[Baby wailing]
Uh, with the chief complaint
of right ear pain.
Hey, Donnie, can you do
something about that?
What?
Seriously?
That--that's not
driving you nuts?
The baby, it won't stop crying.
- Oh, that?
It's music to my ears now.
I think Jesse's the nurse.
Well, can't you--ugh.
[Baby continues wailing]
Fuck.
What the hell is going on?
With what?
- With her.
Can't you make her stop crying?
- She's been fed and changed.
She's cranky from rhinovirus.
[Baby wailing]
Isn't there something
that you can do?
She's due
for her next Tylenol.
Give me a minute.
I'll be right back.
Wait, no, no, no,
I'm not gonna stay here.
[Wailing continues]
What is your problem?
This is precisely why
I didn't go into Pedes.
Okay.
Hey, hey.
Hey, little Miss Sunshine.
Is it time for you
to take a little nap?
That would be so fucking nice.
Yes, it would.
[Baby wailing]
[sighs]
I'm starting to understand
why you got left here.
Hey, shh.
[Singing in Tagalog]
[baby quieting]
[humming]
What's the word from CT?
Nothing intrathoracic,
nothing intra-abdominal.
Propeller just
missed gutting him.
- Very fortunate.
- Okay.
Repeat hemoglobin is eight.
We're holding off
on transfusing.
Plan?
I'll have Mel and Langdon
suture up the lacerations.
- Wait, what?
That could take days.
I--I can't--
- Calm down, Sadness.
I'm kidding.
This is one for my skilled
surgical residents upstairs,
not you Boy Scout butchers.
Boy, I missed you, Yoyo.
Mm. Can't say the same.
Okay, let's take up
this art project.
So about before--
Back to it.
Good talk.
How we doing, Princess?
- All right.
A little bloated.
I had one too many hot dogs
from the truck.
You meant the board, huh?
Gus, our incarcerated patient,
got a spot upstairs.
Looking for our unhoused
patient, Digby, and, of course,
we have Whitaker, Donahue,
and the med students
on these diversion intakes,
but they just keep coming.
Yeah, we may need to start
just sending people up
and ask for forgiveness
instead of permission.
[Phone rings]
- Hello?
Oh, okay.
Yes, I will be right there.
C-suite wants
to see me upstairs.
Ooh, called
to the principal's office
on your first day--
Not a good sign.
- I think I'm a baby whisperer.
- Hey, great.
We'll add Baby Jane Doe
to your patient load.
Forget I said anything.
Where are we with
your deaf patient, Harlow?
Uh, the VRI was a bust, but
the interpreter's on the way.
Figured I'd just give her
a head and belly scan
and go from there.
- No, wait for the interpreter.
No need to give the patient
unnecessary radiation.
And your charting?
Catching up
and checking it twice.
Good.
Hey, have you had a chance
to speak to Langdon today?
Uh, no.
Why? Did he say something?
No, just curious.
How is everything at home
with you and Whitaker?
He's weirder
than you'd expect.
- Hmm.
- Yeah.
But I don't see him
all that much.
He spends a lot of time
at Amy's.
He has a girlfriend?
I don't know what to call it.
The--the farmer
who got burned last year
the day of the mass cas,
his widow, Amy.
Oh, he died?
Yeah, he had burns
on 90% of his body.
His chance of survival
was very slim.
Okay, so I'm an optimist.
The sun doesn't always
come out tomorrow, Annie.
Wait, wasn't she pregnant?
No, she was a young orphan.
No, not Annie. Amy.
- Yes.
Yes, very pregnant and young.
Whitaker is now
seeing this Amy?
And her baby.
He got really close
to the family
when the husband was dying.
He really believed that
the guy would pull through.
He helped her through
the loss of her husband,
and then again
when she had the kid,
and now he spends almost
every weekend at the farm.
Huh.
Plus,
he's on the street team,
and he just wants
to help everybody.
And I just don't wanna see him
taken advantage of, you know?
He's just
a fucking Huckleberry.
Yeah, but he's our
fucking Huckleberry.
I'll talk to him.
Hey, your call.
- Strong deflection.
Well played.
You're the boss.
Or you are until
end of shift today.
Still the boss.
When you see me in here,
still the boss.
Copy that, Boss.
- Dr. Robby, can--
Can I grab you for a second?
Yeah. Sure. What's up?
Um, can't you order
my wife to go home?
I'm sorry.
[Sighs]
My wife's dying,
and you're telling me
there's nothing I can do?
Mr. Hamler, that's not--
No, no.
There's gotta be something.
Please.
It may not seem like much,
but right now,
you being here for her
and respecting her wishes
is the best thing that
you can do for her.
Supporting her and her choices
is the most remarkable gift
that you can give her
at this time.
And the meds we have her on
will help her pain.
And she may get
to a point where
she feels well enough
to go home.
[Sighs]
Give me one second.
Okay, I'm gonna
let you guys get acquainted.
I will be right back.
Oh, oh, oh, excuse me!
I--I'm waiting for Dr. Mohan.
Is she available?
I will try
and find her for you, sir.
Whether you choose to report
or not, we're here for you.
Call me any time.
It could be a month
or a year from now.
I'll follow up with you too.
Thank you.
Thanks.
[Door clicks]
You've had a pap smear before?
Yeah, every few years.
Good.
Same position,
but I'll start with swabs
on the outside,
external genitalia.
Then I'll use a speculum
to get internal swabs.
You ready? Okay.
I'll help you get your feet
in the stirrups.
Good.
Okay. All right.
Now, slide your bottom down.
Oh. Yeah, a little bit more.
A little more.
- Sorry. I--
- I can't.
- Okay. It's okay.
We can take a break.
No problem.
- I don't want a break.
I wanna stop.
- Okay.
Is this about reporting?
Because you can do
this collection
without a police report
for now.
And none of it goes in your
permanent medical record.
I don't wanna do this
anymore.
Tell me why you wanna stop.
[Breathing heavily]
He's my friend.
[Voice breaking]
He knows all my friends.
It was just a dumb--
He was drunk,
he didn't mean it.
It didn't mean anything.
- Okay.
Okay.
It's okay. I understand.
I do.
Ilana, this is a difficult
process, to say the least.
Why don't you take a breather
and come back?
And whatever you wanna do,
we'll do.
Let's go find
the good snacks.
[Door clicks]
[door slamming]
Jesus Christ.
Sorry.
Giving new meaning
to the nickname Crash, huh?
I've been trying to get
to the bathroom
for over an hour now.
Yeah, you and me both,
sister.
[Toilet flushes]
Uh-oh, this can't be good.
Who's this?
That is hospital CEO
Trent Norris.
He's the big boss.
Hmm. Nice outfit.
- Hey, Rockstar.
Gather your staff, please.
Sure, anything you
wanna tell me first?
- No.
- Okay.
Hey, everybody, can you,
uh, gather 'round
and listen up
for a moment, please?
Can I have your attention,
everyone?
Internal disaster at Westbridge
has been identified
as a cyberattack.
[All murmuring]
And now Good Dominion Hospital
has been hit as well.
Their ambulances are being
diverted over to St. Mary's,
but we can expect more walk-ins
and Westbridge diversions.
Uh, for how long?
- We don't know how long.
If the ransom is paid--
Ransom?
Are we next?
Our IT protection system
has blocked thousands
of intrusion attempts
in the hours
since Westbridge was hit
this morning.
But IT believes
we're still vulnerable.
So we're gonna
preemptively shut down
all the computer systems.
- Oh, my God.
- Jesus.
Patient registration,
electronic health records,
lab and radiology interfaces,
email, internet.
You didn't wanna
talk to me first?
consult my department?
I consulted
your fellow attending.
When are we going down?
Soon. Very soon.
Okay, hey, somebody get
a picture of the board.
Quickly, quickly!
We're about to go analog.
[Camera shutter clicks]
- No!
- Oh, my gosh.
[All groaning]
- Phones work?
- They don't work.
- Oh, my gosh.
- Did you get the photo?
Yeah, yeah, I got it.
This is gonna be fun.